Finding aid to the Office of the President Thomas Corwin Mendenhall Files. CA.MS.00032
Smith College Archives
Office of the President Thomas Corwin Mendenhall Files
1956-1982
Smith College Archives
Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin.
CA.MS.00032
34.375 linear feet (85 containers)
Sixth President of Smith College, Professor, history. Contains official records of the Office of the President, incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, news clippings and photographs
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Corwin Mendenhall was the sixth president of Smith College, and the last male president to take office. He accepted the position in 1958, and began work in the fall of 1959. He remained at the college for 16 years, retiring in the spring of 1975. Over the years he became a respected and beloved member of the Smith community, seeing the institution through one of the most divisive periods in American history with skill, sensitivity, and a precocious sense of humor.
Mendenhall arrived at Smith with more than 20 years of experience as an educator and administrator. After receiving degrees from Yale (Class of 1932), and Oxford's Balliol College (B.A. 1935, B.Litt. 1936), he returned to Yale as a professor of history in 1937. Six years later he began taking on administrative duties, first as assistant to the provost (1943-1950), then as the master of Berkeley College (1950-1959). He also had experience with Smith itself by way of his mother, Dorothy Reed Mendenhall, Smith Class of 1895.
Mendenhall was president during a challenging and eventful period for academic administrators across the country. He successfully guided the college through both national and local upheaval, weathering the social and political disputes that have become the hallmark of the 1960s and early 1970s. As the country battled over civil rights, the wars in Southeast Asia, and class iniquity, Smith became one of the thousands of colleges and universities across the country compelled to join the fray both nationally and locally. The legacies of student and faculty activism at Smith can be seen in the curriculum, social regulations, and even administrative structure and procedures. Afro-American Studies (via the Five Colleges), the Bridge Program, and the student exchange program with historically Black colleges all began during these years as a result of local and national struggles for civil rights and class equality. Recruitment programs attempted to diversify the population of students, as well as that of faculty and staff. The debate over coeducation also reached a pinnacle during the Mendenhall years, and the women's movement began to impact the college's curriculum and administrative structure. The Mendenhall Files illustrate the evolution of these issues via the records of individual Smith offices, departments and committees, but also through correspondence with alumnae, students and parents who needed not only to be informed, but in some cases placated in their anger and disappointment.
Changes in the administration and population were accompanied by renovation and addition to the physical layout of the college. Mendenhall oversaw the construction of three new centers and the renovation of several existing buildings. The Clark Science Center, the Fine Arts Center, and the Mendenhall Center for the Performing Arts were all constructed between 1959 and 1975. There was also a significant addition to Neilson Library.
As president of one of the premier women's colleges in the country, Mendenhall was also required to participate in intercollegiate associations such as the Seven Sisters, the Pioneer Valley's Five Colleges, Inc., and the primarily ivy league 12-College Exchange. He was also the Smith representative and point person for many educational organizations and related businesses. His daily schedule was crowded not only with campus activities and responsibilities, but also with speaking engagements and meetings at a variety of locales across the country. The extent of his responsibilities is most apparent in five records series in the collection: Colleges & Universities, Events, Engagements, Intercollegiate Associations, and Non-Smith Organizations. His philosophies and opinions on a variety of issues and events are documented throughout the collection, but are detailed most specifically in the Speeches series.
Throughout his tenure, Mendenhall played key roles in traditional college events, was cheered for his formal and informal talks, and came to be known by successive classes of students and alumnae as "Uncle Tom." He could be seen regularly rowing on Paradise Pond, made frequent appearances at dinners and teas in the student residences, and took an active role in the daily life of the college. He also remained an active educator, teaching in the history department throughout his presidency. When he died On July 18, 1998, at the age of 88, he was mourned by many from the Smith community. The following October, there was a memorial service in the Hills Chapel where friends and spoke about his legacies as an administrator, an educator, and a charismatic character in the history of Smith College.
Scope and Contents
The Mendenhall Files includes material dating from 1956-1982. Some material has been restricted according the College Archives policies. The open records include incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, news clippings and photographs. For more specific information about the contents of the collection see the series descriptions and folder listing below.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eighteen series:
I. Biography
II. Academic Departments
III. Academic Programs
IV. Administrative Issues
V. Administrative Offices
VI. Alumnae
VII. Buildings and Grounds
VIII. Colleges and Universities
IX. Committees Boards
X. Engagements
XI. Events
XII. Faculty and Staff
XIII. Graduate Work
XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
XV. Non-Smith Organizations
XVI. Speeches
XVII. Students
XVIII. Photographs
Related Material
Additional material in the Smith College Archives may be found in the records of other departments and offices of the college, as well as in the personal papers of Thomas Corwin Mendenhall. The papers of Dorothy Reed Mendenhall may also prove useful. They are housed in the Sophia Smith Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The bulk of the collection (85 document boxes) is open to researchers according to the regulations of the College Archives. Some material has been restricted according to the College Archives policies. A small selection is currently open only to employees of the office of origin. College policy and the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act require the restriction of the records of both the Board of Trustees and the Board of Counselors.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the Mendenhall Files were transferred to the College Archives from the Office of the President in a number of accessions dating from the time of his tenure until the present. Some material, however, came from Mendenhall himself after his retirement in 1975, and then from his wife, Cornelia Mendenhall, after his death in 1998. Additional biographical materials, such as news clippings, press releases, and photographs, have been added by the College Archives staff.
Foreign study.; Minority students--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Student movements--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Students, Foreign--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin.; Smith College--Presidents.; Smith College--Curricula.; Smith College--Students.; Ada Comstock Scholars Program.; Five Colleges, Inc.; Smith College. Office of President.; Smith College. Committee on College Planning and Resources.; Smith College. Committee on Social Responsibility.; Smith College. Committee on Student Affairs.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHY, 0.417 linear feet (1 container)
  Scope and Contents
  The records in this series include newsclippings, press releases, and correspondence relating to Mendenhall and his presidency. The bulk of the information relates to the beginning of his career at Smith. There is also information about his family, his tenth anniversary at Smith, and his retirement.
  - News clippings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - News clippings, 1959-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News clippings, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1959-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family, 1959-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Humor, 1959-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Presidency Acceptance Letter Drafts, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Presidency Congratulations Miscellaneous, 1958-1959; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Presidency Congratulations Smith Alumnae, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Presidency Congratulations Smith Faculty & Staff, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Presidency Preparations, 1958-1959; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Presidency Preparations Correspondence with President Wright, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tenth Anniversary at Smith, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Retirement Campus Events, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Retirement Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II. ACADEMIC DEPARTMENTS, 0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
  The files in this series are arranged alphabetically by the most recent name of the department. Included are news clippings, correspondence, and reports from the undergraduate departments of the college. Also included are programs administered by the departments. For example, files from the Smith College Day Schools are included as a sub-series of the Department of Education. However, undergraduate and graduate academic programs administered either jointly by two or more departments, or by a separate and autonomous college office are filed either with Academic Programs or Administrative Offices. Information about Five College joint academic programs in English, History, Music, and the Sciences can be found in the Intercollegiate Associations series.
  - African-American Studies Studies
    General
    See Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations - Five Colleges - Academic Departments & Programs Afro-American
  - American Studies
    See Series III Academic Programs American Studies -and- Series XIII Graduate Work American Studies Diploma Program
  - Anthropology
    See Series II. Academic Departments - Sociology and Anthropology
  - Art
    - General, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ceramics Studio, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Kennedy Chair in the Renaissance, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Summer Seminars Abroad, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Summer Seminars Abroad, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East Asian Languages and Literature, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Economics, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education & Child Study
    see also Series XIII. Grad. Work - Educ. & Child Study
    - Child Study Center, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Day Care Center, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Elisabeth Morrow Morgan Nursery School, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Report of the Evaluation of Smith College's Teacher Educ. Prog., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Smith College Day Schools, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Smith College Day Schools, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Smith College Day Schools, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Smith College Day Schools, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Smith College Day Schools, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - English - General, 1962; 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - English - Writers in Residence, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - French, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Government - Internships, 1963-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History, 1968; 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Music
    - General, 1963; 1971; 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chamber Singers, 1958-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Glee Club, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Peabody Conservatory of Music Summer Sessions, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Smith-Princeton Chamber Chorus, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Valley Music Press/ Smith College Music Archives, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Physical Education, 1961-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    see also Series IX. Committees and Boards - Physical Education and Recreation
  - Physical Education - Rowing, 1962-1963; 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    see also SeriesVII. Buildings and Grounds - Student Residences - Ziskind House Crew
  - Physical Education - Sailing Program, 1960-1964; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Psychology, 1969-1972; undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Psychology - African-American Students, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Religion and Biblical Literature General, 1960; 1964; 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Religion and Biblical Literature Excavation at Tell El Hesi, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Russian, 1960-1975; undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sciences, 1959-1973; undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    see also Series IX. Committees and Boards Science, Committee on
  - Sociology and Anthropology, 1973; undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Spanish, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Theatre and Speech - General, 1966-1969; 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    see also Series XIII. Graduate Work - Theatre and Speech
  - Theatre and Speech - Black Theatre Workshop, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series III. ACADEMIC PROGRAMS, 1.667 linear feet (4 containers)
  The Academic Programs series consists of correspondence, news clippings, and reports regarding academic programs administered by the college outside of the regular operations of the academic departments. Those programs include: the Ada Comstock Scholars Program; the Honors Program; Pre-medical studies; Smith Scholars/Independent Study; the National Defense Education Act Institutes, interdepartmental courses and majors; Operations Crossroads Africa, Junior Year Abroad; and a number of exchange programs. The exchange programs involve colleges in India and Nigeria, as well as historically African-American colleges and universities within the United States. The Junior Year Abroad program files include information on studies in Toronto, Canada; Paris, France; Munich, Germany; Madrid, Spain; Geneva, Switzerland; Florence and Rome, Italy; Japan; the Philippines; China; and Latin America.
  - Ada Comstock Scholars, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Studies, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    see also Series XIII. Grad Work - Amer. Studies Diploma Progam
  - Honors Program, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Honors Program Theses Publication, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interdepartmental Courses and Majors, 1958; 1960; 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Junior Year Abroad
    - Annual Reports, 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Africa, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      see also Series III. Academic Programs - Operations Crossroads Africa
    - Canada Toronto, 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - China, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - England, 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - France, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      see also Series VI. Alumnae - Former Juniors in France
    - France, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - France, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - France, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Germany, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Germany, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Germany, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Italy Florence, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Italy Florence, 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Italy Rome, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Japan, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Latin America, 1971; 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Philippines, 1962-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Spain, 1959-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Switzerland, 1959-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Switzerland, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Switzerland, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Defense Education Act Institutes, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Defense Education Act Institutes, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Defense Education Act Institutes, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Operations Crossroads Africa, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    see also Series III. Academic Progs - JYA - Africa
  - Pre-Medical, 1968; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Smith Scholars/Independent Study, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Student/Faculty Exchange with Historically Black Colleges, 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    see also Series XIV. Intercollegiate Assoc - Five Colleges - Mary Holmes Junior College
  - Student Exchange with India, 1958-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Student Exchange with the University of Ibidan, Nigeria, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series IV. ADMINISTRATIVE ISSUES, 1.25 linear feet (3 containers)
  The files in the Administrative Issues series document activity in the President's Office which is either of a general nature, requiring the attention of only the president and his closest assistants, or requiring the participation of a number of administrative bodies at once. Included in this series are records relating to a number of general issues, such as administrative structure, the curriculum, the college calendar, disaster preparedness, bomb threats, and energy conservation. The issues generally requiring the attention of the president and his assistants include the president's annual reports, town and gown relations, secondary education, and emeritus Smith presidents and their families. Issues that involve a number of administrative bodies include computer and audiovisual equipment and facilities, and the confidentiality of student records. There is also a collection of miscellaneous correspondence handled by the President's Office.
  - Administrative Structure, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Audio-Visual Equipment & Facilities, 1965-1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Audio-Visual Equipment & Facilities Instructional TV Report, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Audio-Visual Equipment & Facilities Ad Hoc Committee Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bomb Threats, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Calendar, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coeducation
    See Series IX. Committees & Boards - College Planning & Resources, Cttee on
  - Computers Academic Uses, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    see also Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations - 5 Colleges Computing Center -and- Series V. Administrative Offices - Computer Center
  - Computers Administrative Uses, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Computers Administrative Uses, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Confidentiality of Student Records, 1969; 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Curriculum
    - General, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Arts vs. Science Gloria Heath Proposal, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Interim, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Interterm, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Disaster Preparedness - Civil Defense, 1959-1965; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Disaster Preparedness - Disaster Plan, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Disaster Preparedness - Fire Safety, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Emeritus Smith Presidents & Their Families - Davis, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Emeritus Smith Presidents & Their Families - Neilson, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Emeritus Smith Presidents & Their Families - Wright, 1959; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    see also Series I. Biography - Presidency Preparations
  - Energy Conservation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Service/Social Responsibility, 1959-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Secondary Education
    - General, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      see also Series IV. Administrative Issues - Town & Gown Relations Northampton Public Schools
    - Hill House School Trial, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Kent School, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Miss Hall's School, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Northfield & Mount Herman Schools, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Williston Academy, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Town & Gown Relations
    - General, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      see also Series IX. Committees & Boards - Smith-Northampton Ad Hoc Cttee - and- Series V. Admin Offices - Financial Aid Scholarships - Northampton-Hatfield Scholarships
    - Academy of Music, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Academy of Music, 1963-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Academy of Music, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Academy of Music - McCarter Theatre of Princeton, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Arcadia Wildlife Sanctuary, 1963-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Autumn Inn, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clarke School for the Deaf, 1959-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      see also Series XIII. Graduate Work - Educ and Child Study - Clark School Teacher Training
    - Cooley Dickinson Hospital, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Coolidge, Calvin: See Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations - 5 Colleges - Museum of Natural History Proposal
    - Forbes Library, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hampshire Community Action Commission, 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hampshire County Family Planning Services, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Hatfield, Town of, 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mill River, 1964; 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Northampton Affordable Housing, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Northampton City Government, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Northampton City Government, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Northampton Chamber of Commerce, 1960-1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Northampton Community Chest, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Northampton Fire & Police Depts, 1960-1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Northampton Public Schools, 1960-1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Northampton State Hospital, 1963-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Northampton Welfare Service Advisory Board, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - St. John's Church, 1963; 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Transportation, Public, 1961-1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Women's Education, 1960-1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1959-1975; undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Series V. ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICES, 7.083 linear feet (18 containers)
  The Administrative Offices series is the largest series in the Mendenhall Files. It includes correspondence and reports from individual offices as well as news clippings and other general information about their activities and functions. The files are arranged alphabetically by the most recent name of the office.
  - Administrative Data Processing, 1960; 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Annual Reports, 1959-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Equal Rights Amendment, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minority Students, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minority Students, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minority Students, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Minority Students Enrollment Lists, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Transfer Students, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Advancement
    See Series V. Administrative Offices - Development
  - Bookstore, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Business Manager - Annual Reports, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General, 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - College-Owned Vehicles, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Telephones, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Campus School
    See Series II. Academic Depts - Educ. & Child Study Smith College Day Schools
  - Career Services
    See Series V. Administrative Offices - Vocational Office
  - Chaplain - General, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Catholic Assistant Chaplain, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Human Relations Training Group, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Computer Center, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    see also Series IV. Administrative Issues - Computers -and- Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations - 5 Colleges - Computing Center
  - Dean of the College, 1959-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)